<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.0.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-04-10T19:38:45-05:00</updated><id>https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Statement to the Court</title><subtitle>We are here to help each other get through this thing, whatever it is.</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Socialize Pharma</title><link href="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/pharma/socialism/market%20failure/2020/04/10/Socialize-Pharma.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Socialize Pharma" /><published>2020-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-10T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/pharma/socialism/market%20failure/2020/04/10/Socialize-Pharma</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/pharma/socialism/market%20failure/2020/04/10/Socialize-Pharma.html">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-04-10-Socialize-Pharma.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/statement-to-the-court/images/copied_from_nb/images/pills.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At &lt;a href=&quot;https://jacobinmag.com/2020/04/socialize-big-pharma-antibiotics-artificial-intelligence/&quot;&gt;Jacobin, Leigh Phillips uses some rare good news in the fight against antibiotic resistance&lt;/a&gt; - the discovery, by a deep learning algorithm, of a novel antibiotic - as a jumping-off point to advocate for socializing the pharmaceutical industry. And while he lays out the basic case for doing so well, he misses the fundamental absurdity of our current financing system for drug discovery. The case for socializing pharma becomes much stronger once our current system of publicly funded biomedical research and government-granted patents is taken into account.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The argument from first principles for socializing drug discovery and production is straight forward. Pharmaceutical companies derive the most profit from drugs that patients have to take every day for an indeterminate period - mostly to manage chronic conditions like high cholesterol, hypertension, and diabetes. Drugs that are needed infrequently and for a short period (e.g. antibiotics) or drugs that cure or prevent a disease (e.g. vaccines) are not as profitable. As a result, pharmaceutical companies expend endless resources on developing new drugs for diseases for which effective treatments already exist while completely ignoring entire classes of drugs for which there is a desperate need for new therapies. As Phillips points out this isn't so much a failing of pharmaceutical companies themselves as a systematic failure of capitalism. Because the capitalist measure of value, profit, does not account for actual human need we are left with the absurd situation of billions being spent on developing new statins while facing the very real possibility of not having effective antibiotics. The simplest solution is to remove the profit incentive, socialize the discovery and production of drugs (preferably internationally), and direct it towards fulfilling real human needs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is especially true when one considers the extent to which the pharmaceutical industry is already subsidized by the American taxpayer. As Phillips points out, most (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biocompare.com/Life-Science-News/347047-NIH-Funding-Behind-All-New-Drug-Approvals-by-FDA-from-2010-2016/&quot;&gt;if not all&lt;/a&gt;) of the basic research that results in novel therapies are carried out in university labs and funded primarily by public grants via the National Institutes of Health (NIH). These grants, about 40 billion, account for more than a third of total pharmaceutical research. The real give away though, &lt;a href=&quot;https://truthout.org/articles/sanders-khanna-bill-would-stop-propping-up-drug-prices/&quot;&gt;as Dean Baker so rightfully and regularly points out&lt;/a&gt;, is the government-granted patent protections for new drugs. These patents allow pharmaceutical companies to sell drugs for several hundred to several thousands of times the cost of production and drive a majority of their 440+ billion (2.2% of GDP in 2018) revenue per year. Baker estimates that if the government simply directly paid the entire costs of research upfront the savings to patients would be on the order of 400 billion annually!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Socializing pharma would not only redirect drug discovery towards fulfilling crucial medical needs but it would massively improve the affordability and access to medicines. It is a no brainer and should be part of any Left plan to reform our broken health care system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>debs</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">The Goldfinch</title><link href="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/books/fiction/recommendations/gatekeeping/2020/04/09/The-Goldfinch.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Goldfinch" /><published>2020-04-09T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-09T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/books/fiction/recommendations/gatekeeping/2020/04/09/The-Goldfinch</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/books/fiction/recommendations/gatekeeping/2020/04/09/The-Goldfinch.html">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-04-09-The-Goldfinch.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/statement-to-the-court/images/copied_from_nb/images/goldfinch.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I read Donna Tartt's brilliant 2013 novel &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; 6 years late and was mesmerized. The immediate impression I had was one of pleasure, the deep satisfaction of witnessing another human being achieve mastery in their craft. As a lifelong football fan, I viscerally felt this description of another slate of 4 PM kickoffs winding down:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;On game day, until five o’clock or so, the white desert light held off the essential Sunday gloom—autumn sinking into winter, loneliness of October dusk with school the next day—but there was always a long still moment toward the end of those football afternoons where the mood of the crowd turned and everything grew desolate and uncertain, onscreen and off, the sheet-metal glare off the patio glass fading to gold and then gray, long shadows and night falling into desert stillness, a sadness I couldn’t shake off, a sense of silent people filing toward the stadium exits and cold rain falling in college towns back east.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tartt is a gifted writer who spent 11 years on &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; and it shows.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beyond the beautiful prose, the book is full of profound meditations on the relation of art and mortality; the experience of trauma, substance abuse, and ennui; the liminal state of participating in a social strata to which one can never be fully accepted; and how the love of the idea of a person can be impervious to their reality. And of course, Boris, the most gloriously original fictional character I've encountered in some time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was excited then to get online and read what others thought of it. I was aware - it was on the front material of my digital copy - that the book had won the 2014 Pulitzer Prize and so expected a cavalcade of praise. Instead I was dismayed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vanityfair.com/culture/2014/07/goldfinch-donna-tartt-literary-criticism&quot;&gt;critical firestorm&lt;/a&gt; that the book had engendered upon its release.
The criticism of The Goldfinch wasn't so much about the novel itself as it was about what the critics perceived the novel was claiming to be. In their minds &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; presented itself as literature which they decided it was most decidedly not. That, in fact, by being widely read and acclaimed as such &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; was doing the entire idea of literature a grave disservice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This sort of critique was exemplified by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2013/10/21/the-new-curiosity-shop&quot;&gt;James Wood in the New Yorker&lt;/a&gt;. Wood did not like the book. He thought it's prose and themes childish (how this can be the case when one of the major threads of the novel is substance abuse and dependence is beyond me, but I digress), it's characters out of central casting from a fairy tale, and it's narrative too fantastic to be engaging. Worst of all for Wood, &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; claims to be something that it is decidedly not:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;p&gt;Tartt’s consoling message, blared in the book’s final pages, is that what will survive of us is great art, but this seems an anxious compensation, as if Tartt were unconsciously acknowledging that the 2013 “Goldfinch” may not survive the way the 1654 “Goldfinch” has.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a criticism of the book on its merits. It is a criticism of what Woods perceives to be the authors intent. The book is not only bad, it is especially bad because Wood claims that Tartt intends it as literature.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two levels on which this bothers me. First, it implies that trying and failing to create literature is somehow worthy of special disapproval. That the mere thought of attaining greatness opens one up for exceptional criticism. Second, it further implies the existence of a sanctified group of people with unique ability to judge whether a book is great or merely tries to be great. People like James Wood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why would a critic, who one assumes loves literature, seek to discourage people from attempting to write literature? Why is a book especially bad because it attempts and fails to be great? If anything such an attempt should be recognized and bemoaned as a misfortune, a writer as obviously talented as Tartt encouraged to try again. It's almost as if some critics are more jealous of their prerogative then they are devoted to their canon. But that would be judging critics on our perceptions of their intent, and that would be unfair wouldn't it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fortunately for you, dear reader, Wood is wrong on the merits of Tartt's novel. &lt;em&gt;The Goldfinch&lt;/em&gt; is a brilliant book and you should read it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>debs</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">About Wisconsin</title><link href="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/politics/gop/power/2020/04/08/About-Wisconsin.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="About Wisconsin" /><published>2020-04-08T00:00:00-05:00</published><updated>2020-04-08T00:00:00-05:00</updated><id>https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/politics/gop/power/2020/04/08/About-Wisconsin</id><content type="html" xml:base="https://adamwri.github.io/statement-to-the-court/politics/gop/power/2020/04/08/About-Wisconsin.html">&lt;!--
#################################################
### THIS FILE WAS AUTOGENERATED! DO NOT EDIT! ###
#################################################
# file to edit: _notebooks/2020-04-08-About-Wisconsin.ipynb
--&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;container&quot; id=&quot;notebook-container&quot;&gt;
        
    
    
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing code_cell rendered&quot;&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
    

&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/statement-to-the-court/images/copied_from_nb/images/wisconsin_covid.png&quot; alt=&quot;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;cell border-box-sizing text_cell rendered&quot;&gt;&lt;div class=&quot;inner_cell&quot;&gt;
&lt;div class=&quot;text_cell_render border-box-sizing rendered_html&quot;&gt;
&lt;p&gt;On April 6, 2020 John Roberts sentenced an unknown number of Wisconsinites to their deaths. In a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vox.com/2020/4/6/21211378/supreme-court-coronavirus-voting-rights-disenfranchise-rnc-dnc&quot;&gt;5-4 decision&lt;/a&gt;, the Republican Supreme Court majority ruled that absentee ballots for the April 7 Wisconsin primary - in which a critical state Supreme Court seat was up for election - would only be counted if they were postmarked by that date. This despite two inconvenient facts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Hundreds of thousands of the 1.2M voters who requested absentee ballots were not expected to have received them by April 7.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Like the rest of the United States, Wisconsin is beset by a pandemic caused by a highly contagious, airborne coronavirus.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of this decision, Wisconsinites were faced with a grim choice the next day: dramatically increase their chance of infection (and further community spread) by venturing out into public to cast their vote or stay home and accept their disenfranchisement. Perhaps shocked by their depravity in creating this dilemma, the right-wing ideologues on the Court left their opinion unsigned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This episode is disturbing in of itself - the Republican Party, for narrow partisan advantage, engineered a situation where voters had to chose between their safety and their franchise. But the reason it is the subject of my inaugural blog is it is illustrative of three of the worst pathologies of the modern GOP:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Power as the ultimate end in itself. The Court made this ruling because it made it more likely that the GOP would retain a majority on the Wisconsin State Supreme Court. That majority in turn will rule in ways to further GOP minority rule in one of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brennancenter.org/our-work/analysis-opinion/gerrymandering-meets-coronavirus-wisconsin&quot;&gt;most gerrymandered states in American history&lt;/a&gt;. This circular logic of power as both a means and an end in itself is &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Reactionary_Mind&quot;&gt;fundamental to the conservative psyche&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The centrality of voter suppression to the GOP electoral strategy. Due to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://archive.thinkprogress.org/republican-party-is-running-on-unpopular-ideas-in-2020-53f5b1ae666f/&quot;&gt;deep unpopularity&lt;/a&gt; of their agenda and the changing demographic profile of the country, the GOP recognizes that they cannot win free and fair elections. To compete electorally, they must systematically suppress the vote of likely Democratic voters (minorities, urbanites, the young). This is a particular obsession of Chief Justice John Roberts, &lt;a href=&quot;https://crooked.com/articles/john-roberts-is-not-your-friend/&quot;&gt;who somehow maintains a positive approval rating&lt;/a&gt; amongst Democrats while systematically &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.politico.com/magazine/story/2015/08/john-roberts-voting-rights-act-121222&quot;&gt;working to undermine their ability to vote&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Extremism. Not even the physical safety of fellow citizens is worth protecting in pursuit of partisan advantage.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These themes will recur regularly as the American political system descends further into chaos and dysfunction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>debs</name></author><summary type="html"></summary></entry></feed>